Finding Aid for Church of the Messiah (Detroit, Mich.) Records 1875-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Church of the Messiah (Detroit, Mich.) Records 1875-1998
Church of the Messiah (Detroit, Mich.)
2.75 linear feet
Episcopal Church in Detroit, Michigan with long history of involvement in social action activities and urban ministry. Records include minutes, registers, scrapbooks and photographs.
98116 Ba 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred through Rev. Stephen Bartlett, Rector, in June 1998. Donor no. 8735
The collection is open for research.
The Church of the Messiah began as a mission of Christ Church, Detroit, holding its initial service in November of 1874. Four years later, the first chapel of the Messiah was erected at the corner of Mt. Elliott and East Fort. Messiah was officially recognized as a Diocesan Mission in 1880 and achieved parish status in 1885 with the Rev. G. Mott Williams (later to become Bishop of Marquette) as its first rector. The congregation continued to expand and by 1897 had outgrown its chapel, worshipping in the parish hall.
In 1899, the Messiah congregation made an agreement to buy the materials of St. Paul's Church at Shelby and Congress (the oldest Episcopal congregation in Detroit) for $1,000, and to use the material to construct a new church as much like St. Paul's as possible. It cost $28,000 to move and rebuild the structure. Many who wished to see the old church they knew and loved preserved, contributed toward the expense. Relocation began in 1900, was completed a year later, and a dedication service was held November 3, 1901 -- twenty-seven years after Messiah began and fifty years after the original St. Paul's was built.
Church of the Messiah became a large and diverse congregation in its new location on East Grand Boulevard and prospered as the neighborhood around it flourished. Well-known Detroiters of the early part of the century were members, as well as blue-collar workers and middle-class families. In 1922, a large parish house was built to house the abundant activities of the church. There were 1,500 communicants in the 1920s, and the church continued to serve the neighborhood effectively through the decade that followed. A decline began in the late 40s, however, as families began to move out of the area. Membership and attendance dipped significantly in the 1950s and 1960s as the neighborhood fell into urban decline.
In 1970, Archdeacon Irving Mayson envisioned a black / white team ministry to bring renewed life to both Messiah and another east side parish, Church of the Epiphany. (Epiphany, located at Cadillac and Kercheval, was organized in 1895 and admitted as a parish in 1911). In 1971, Ron Spann and Dean Cole were hired, soon to be joined by others who shared a vision for urban ministry. Influenced by charismatic renewal at Houston's Church of the Redeemer, Spann and Cole arrived with a vision for Christian community and a desire for strong commitment to the neighborhood. Several months later, Church of the Redeemer sent two of its members to spend a year at Church of the Messiah. The roots of a new community were formed as people moved into the neighborhood and drove in from the suburbs to become part of the vision. An active lay leadership evolved.
By 1974, Church of the Epiphany was sold and ministry was consolidated at Church of the Messiah. Some members left, including Cole, but many others were drawn to the congregation. Extended family households were established for members interested in a shared economic lifestyle. Work crews were established for parishioners who needed a structured work environment. An accredited private elementary school and a day care center were created; a food purchasing group organized; and a performing team, The Fisherfolk, ministered through the arts.
In the second half of the 1970s, the congregation addressed issues well beyond immediate boundaries. A global consciousness toward broad-based social issues emerged, and Messiah members included these concerns in their worship. The Messiah Peace Ministry held retreats to focus on resisting the arms race. Members embarked on peace missions to Nigeria, South Africa, and Nicaragua. They joined with churches in Houston, Washington D.C., Cincinnati, Cleveland, and Berkeley in 1977 to form a socially oriented group called "Community of Communities." Addressing bigotry in all its manifestations, including racism, classism, and sexism, was high on the agenda.
In the meantime, however, the predominately black, lower-income neighborhood surrounding Church of the Messiah continued to deteriorate, and concern for justice hit closer to home. Neighborhood involvement led to the purchase and ownership of threatened nearby apartment buildings. The buildings eventually became cooperatives owned and operated by tenants, a pioneering initiative consciously designed to empower lower-income residents. The housing corporation sought to build community spirit and to address the needs of a disenfranchised population, not only in housing but in economics, crime, health, education, social welfare, and political empowerment.
By 1986, a dynamic full-time youth director provided tutoring, weekly discussion classes, scholarships, field trips, recreation, and summer employment. Over the years youth ministry leaders continued to provide educational, spiritual and recreational activities for youth in the neighborhood. Nutritional needs of the elderly were served by the Senior Citizens Food Pantry, and many people living in foster-care facilities and nursing homes along the Boulevard became members of the congregation.
The community continues to grapple with and to respond to change, convinced that the future of the church rests essentially with the quality of the relationship it shares with those in its neighborhood. What was once a largely white middle-class congregation of people, many of whom at one time came into the city from the suburbs, is now a racially mixed, neighborhood church with a unique and unusually committed congregation and a rich and notable history.
The records of the Church of the Messiah (2.5 linear ft., 1875-1988) span most of it's years -- from establishment in 1874 through several transitional periods and into the late 80s. The collection consists mainly of ledger books and record books, collected material pertaining to church history, scrapbooks of clippings, and photographs. There are four series in the Church of the Messiah collection: Minutes, Registers, Scrapbooks and Miscellaneous Material, and Photographs.
Researchers should note that Church of the Messiah collaborated in ministry with Epiphany Episcopal Church in the early 1970s. The two churches merged in 1974. The Bentley Historical Library holds a small collection of Epiphany records (1 linear ft. and 4 oversized volumes).
Subjects:
Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Social services--Michigan--Detroit.; Church of the Messiah (Detroit, Mich.); Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Church architecture--Michigan--Detroit.; Churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Churches.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Minutes
  Minutes of meetings cover the life of the church from its earliest days through 1963 except for a gap between 1894 and 1924. These volumes are detailed and offer significant information regarding activities and commitments made by clergy and church membership in those years.
  - 1883-1894 (Box 1)
  - 1924-1934 (Box 1)
  - January 1935-February 1957 (Box 1)
  - March 1957-November 1963 (Box 1)
- Registers
  Registers include directories of services, a complete run from February 1926 through December 1979. The series also holds less inclusive financial ledgers. Financial data is incomplete for the years 1895 to 1899 and 1902 to 1975 and concludes in 1983. There is also a volume of annual reports from December 1926 to 1929 and a member registry for 1881 to 1901, which includes a brief history.
  - Services
    - April 1897-December 1926 (Box 1)
    - February 1926-June 1931 (Box 2)
    - September 1931-January 1943 (Box 2)
    - September 1971-December 1979 (Box 2)
  - Financial
    - June 1880-April 1895 (Box 2)
    - May 1899-December 1902 (Box 2)
    - 1975-1983 (Box 2)
      (mainly real estate records)
  - Other Registers
    - Annual Reports December 1926-January 1929 (Box 2)
    - Member Register 1881-1901 (Box 2)
      (includes brief history)
- Scrapbooks
  Scrapbooks in the collection hold a wealth of research material. Of particular note is a volume containing newspaper articles on the building of the church and clippings documenting community activities from 1875 to 1910. There are also black and white photographs illustrating the evolution of the building process and printed material celebrating events held in Messiah's earliest years. Items were removed from volumes with brittle pages, and the material stored in acid-free folders.
  - Newspaper Articles re: Church Construction 1886-1901 (Box 3)
  - Peace Offerings for Repair of Roof 1945 (Box 3)
  - Records of Literature Used for Campaign and Canvas 1926-1928 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook Material: Photographs, printed items, newspaper articles, misc. 1897-1958, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous Material
  Miscellaneous Material includes a comprehensive history written by church members. Entitled A History of the Church of the Messiah, the booklet documents the community through 1992, focusing most heavily on recent decades. The vitality of the 70s and 80s is further evident in a file of collected material -- an excellent source for detailed information on the activism of the church in these years. Sadder days are also documented. The series includes the text of a 1988 memorial service held for Michelle Rougeau, a young nurse, long-standing member of the church, and president of a newly organized housing cooperative, who was murdered in her apartment.
  - Address at Laying of Corner Stone 1901 (Box 3)
  - Collected Material 1980-1993 (Box 3)
  - Day Care Manual 1982 (Box 3)
  - History of the Church of the Messiah (Box 3)
  - Memorial Service for Michelle Rougeau 1988 (Box 3)
  - Messiah Housing: Agency Disclosure Statement 1998 (Box 3)
  - Reorganization 1918 (Box 3)
  - Brown Book 1920s (Box 3)
    (cook book)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series offers visual evidence of a spirited and committed congregation. Color snapshots include portraits, images captured at outreach and social gatherings, and pictures of children in the learning center. Photographs were removed from plastic albums and placed in acid-free folders.
  - Messiah Learning Center 1974-1975 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous; includes choir 1931 and confirmation class 1981 (Box 3)
  - Church Activities and People 1983-1988 (Box 3)
  - Members 1983-1988 (Box 3)